Previously we only dealt with adding the files to the project. Lets have a look at deletion.
Now I`m in one of the previous states of the project and will delete the ".gitignore"
The ".idea" was added here to ignore the Webstorm service files.
But ignoring it here is not exactly right as it should be ignored via some global ignore file,
as editor choice is a personal preference and it`s not related to this project at all.
If I have other project somewhere then ".idea" should be ignored there too.
As you see, this should definitely be a global-level setting.
So let me set the global ignore file, open it in the editor and put it there.
Closing, getting back to the project. Now I dont need the local ".gitignore", so Im deleting it.
Lets "git status" it.
I remind you that index stores the list of all project files that are tracked by Git.
We have a file missing now and it is present in the index, so "git status" has noticed it.
To save this change in the repository, we have to add it to the index first. Lets use "git add" for that.
Its a little bit funny as theres no ".gitignore" file any more.
So "git add" is actually adding the fact of its deletion to the index, or looking at it from the technical perspective
it just deletes ".gitignore" from the list of the indexed files. Now if I execute "git status",
we see the changes moved from "not staged for commit"
to "to be committed". So the change is in the index and now we can finally save it in our repository.
"git commit -m Cleanup"
As the message here consists of one word only, we dont need quotes. Please note: a little peculiarity of the image.
This file is still in the repository as repository stores the history of all the changes.
Just this particular illustration shows the last state of the repository.
And things that were, they are somewhere behind it. We'll have a look on how to get access to it later on.
To remove the fiels from git there is also a "git rm" command. Here we show one or multiple ways.
If we point to a directory we need the "-r" flag. E.g. like that to delete the "src" directory.
This command makes in one step things we did in two.
Namely it deletes from the work directory and adds the change to the index.
"git rm" - same as just deleting
and "git add", so the state of the project is like that if I run it
We saw a usual deletion already, so let me run it in another way, with a "--cached" flag.
It will delete from the index, but keep in the working directory. Now the state of the project became like that.
Please, note, if I type "git status" then you see that the "src" directory remains,
because we used the "--cached" flag. But it is "untracked" now. So git doesnt track it. Its not in the index any more.
To add it back to the index: "git add src". Executing... Oh, snap! The changes are not in the working directory again.
In the index in the current state of the repository files are same.
We used the "git rm --cached" command to delete "script.js" from the index first and then "git add" to get it back.
So there are no changes.
In real life "rm --cached" is used to files which are to be kept in the working directory,
but not in the git.
For example, because these files are editor related and were added accidentally. For that after deletion they are added into ".gitignore".
Lets note that "--cached" flag is used in some other git commands.
Its main idea is that the operation is only done with the index and the working directory remains the same.
Id like to draw your attention to one more aspect of the "rm" command, the one that is actually inherent by many other git commands.
Git tries to be on the safe side, so that if I have some changes and I didnt save these changes to the repository yet,
then the attempt to remove such a file "git rm" will lead to an error.
Git complains because if you delete now then the unsaved changes will just fade away.
They were not saved into the repository, so that git will not help to restore them if it occures that we have accidentally deleted them,
and by this it draws our attention to it.
If we really want to delete such a file we have to use one more common flag: "-f".
This flag exists in many git commands. It allows to ignore the warnings and make git to actually execute the command.
So that if I run it now, then "index.html" will be deleted from the working directory and from the index.
So we had a look at the ways to add the files and remove the files from the repository.
Rename remains. Its the easiest, as from the gits perspective there is no renaming at all.
E.g lets take the "index.html" and rename it to "hello.html".
Now if I type "git status" I see 2 changes.
First: the old "index.html" file was deleted. Second: new named "hello.html" have been added.
So git percepts renaming as the aggregation of two commands: deletion of the old file and creation of the new one.
Now lets add both of these changes to the index: "git add ."
And run the "git status" again.
Now "git status" already sees that there was a rename.
Why could not git understand it previously, when we called the "git status"?
Thats because at the moment of "git status" call "hello.html" file was not known yet.
Git didnt know whats inside there and therefore could not understand that its one and the same file.
And when we add the file into the index, git writes it in its inner storage
calculates the control summ and can understand that it has this file already and show this nice message.
Therefore if I make "git commit" now this change will be written into the repository.
As with "rm" in git there is a special command "git mv",
that allows to make these two operations at once e.g. "git mv index.html hello.html".
Simultaneously renamed the file in the work directory and added the information to the index about it.
So, in this issue we had a look at how the deletion and renaming is handled in git.
The main conclusion is the following: deletion and renaming doesnt need any special commands.
One can just make it in the working directory and add the change via "git add".
And everything will just work fine. But there are commands for your convenience.
"git rm" deletes the files from the working directory and from the index. Therefore its a summation of the usual deletion from the disk
and adding the information on it to the index.
The most common flag is probably "-r" for deleting the directories.
"-f" - for deleting the files with changes, that were not saved into the repository.
You have to keep in mind that all the unsaved changes will be lost,
as we didnt save the changes to git and we cant get them out of it later. So if we want to be able to rollback the deletion later
we should commit the changes first and then delete the file.
And "--cached" will only delete from the index.
This flag is used when we want to remove the file from the repository but keep it in the working directory,
e.g if we know we will need it for something later on.
"git mv" command works in the similar way. It renames in the working directory and
adds the information to the index.